A Guide to the Elizabeth Fine Papers, c.1983-2012
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Elizabeth Fine Papers, c.1983-2012
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Fine, Elizabeth
Ms2015-041
6.2 Cubic Feet 5 boxes; 1 oversize folder
The Elizabeth Fine Papers include papers and materials collected by Fine during her tenure as a professor at Virginia Tech. Fine taught in the Department of Religion and Culture from 1979 until her retirement in 2015. The collection includes research and subject files on aspects of Appalachian culture and history; papers from her instruction, departmental, and administrative activities; and files on historic buildings on campus, particularly the history, renovation, and reopening of "Solitude."
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Elizabeth Fine Papers were donated to Special Collections in July 2015.
Biographical Note
Dr. Fine joined the Virginia Tech Faculty in 1979. From 1993-1999, she was the coordinator for he Appalachian Studies Program. Following that, she served as director of the Humanities Program in the Center for Interdisciplinary Studies from 1999 to 2003 and was the inaugural chair of the Department of Interdisciplinary Studies from 2003 to 2007. In 2007, she returned to leadership in the humanities, eventually co-founding and co-directing the Master of Arts Program in Material Culture and Public Humanities. In this role, she helped develop its curriculum, set policies and procedures, recruited and advised students, designed and taught new courses, and was a mentor to the next generation of museum, non-profit, public humanities professionals. As reflected in the collection, she also led and continued to maintain efforts to preserve Solitude and its remaining outbuilding. Dr. Fine retired from Virginia Tech in 2015.
For additional information:
http://liberalarts.vt.edu/faculty-directory/religion-and-culture-faculty/elizabeth-fine.html
https://vtnews.vt.edu/articles/2015/09/091415-clahs-emeritafine.html
Scope and Contents
The Elizabeth Fine Papers include papers and materials collected by Fine during her tenure as a professor at Virginia Tech. Fine taught in the Department of Religion and Culture from 1979 until her retirement in 2015. The collection includes research and subject files on aspects of Appalachian culture and history; papers from her instruction, departmental, and administrative activities; and files on historic buildings on campus, particularly the history, renovation, and reopening of "Solitude."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. Within each series, the files are in their original order as they were received from the donor.
Series I: Appalachian Studies Files consists of subject and research files on a variety of topics relating to Appalachia. These include, but are not limited to locations in southwest Virginia, symposia and conferences, local organizations or institutions, topics (like coal mining, strikes, foodways), and materials from events and grants.
Series II: Instruction, Department, and Academic Administrative Materials relating to Virginia Tech includes personal and professional research materials, course syllabi and work, extensive information on the Appalachian Studies program at Virginia Tech, and the program's connection to interdisciplinary studies and other departments on campus.
Series III: Historic Structures at Virginia Tech (mostly Solitude) contains a large amount of information on Solitude, its outbuildings, and their history as a building on campus (including fundraising, renovations, images, planning documents for past restorations, historic reports, images, and interviews/articles). This series also includes a small amount historic preservation information about the campus generally.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; University Archives; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; University History
Corporate Names:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. College of Liberal Arts & Human Sciences (2003-); Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Department of Religion and Culture; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Department of Philosophy and Religion
Persons:
Fine, Elizabeth
Contents List
- Series I: Appalachian Studies Files
  - Tall Tales & Short History of Newport, Virginia, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christiansburg Institute MOU (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fine - Vita Film Review (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Giles County Information (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chestnut Tree From P.C. Collection (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roanoke Times ad, 25 years of Appalachian Studies (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pearisburg News, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budget - The Appalachian Way (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Appalachian Way (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - God in These Mountains Symposium, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mountain Life & Work (Magazine), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Appalachian Studies Association (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Preserving Community Identity in the New River Valley, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New River Community Partners Work Plan (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newport Conference (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - VFH Grant Report (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newport Volunteer Project, Perry Mountain (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newport Partnership (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pittston Coal Strike, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Women & Pittston Strike (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fine, "Only a Miner" speech. Coal Mining Day, April 23, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ASPO (Appalachian People's Service Organization) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ASPO (Appalachian People's Service Organization) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Coal Camp Memories - Show (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Log of Materials - McCombs (D. McCombs Collection Notes) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Appalachian Way (Student Club) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Spring Time/April In Appalachia (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Radford University, Appalachian Regional Studies Center, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Appalachian Studies Newsclippings - Appalachian Way Scrapbook (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fine, Betty: Correspondence & Awards (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence: Knowbler, Alfred, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Various Appalachian Newsletters, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Appalachian Corps (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Speer, Jean Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Newsletter for the Appalachian Teachers Network, "Stitches," 1995 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Appalachian Studies Conference Blacksburg, 5th Annual, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Appalachian News, Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Consortium News" Appalachian Studies Newsletter, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Wally Inchworm (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Greenbrier Ghost: Yolanda Lipinski (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Michael Kirkland (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Quilting in Appalachia (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - "Be a Humanities Turkey" Material Culture, Center for Prog. In Humanities (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Being a Joines: A Life in the Brush Mtns. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blacks in Appalachia (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bottom Creek Land Study for Nature Consercancy (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Boyd, C. Clifford, Jr; Prehistoric and Hisoric Human Adaptation in Appalachia (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Appalachia Voices (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mountain Musicians (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jabbour, Alan; Folklife today on the Blue Ridge Parkway (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Maw's Moonshine Honey (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foodways in Appalachia (ARC) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ms. Ora & Ms. Etta: Folk History (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Parkway Historic Study (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Smithsonian Documentation (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Appalachian Corps (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wildwood House Museum (WV) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newport Handouts (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Stepping Grant (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stepping Conf. Presenter Vitas & Abstracts, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Stepping Conf. Budget Details (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Stepping Conf. Papers (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Stepping Conf. Responses & Letters (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Stepping Conf. Invitations & CFPs (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Stepping Conf. Grants (AA&Vfn), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Stepping Conf. Evaluations, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Stepping Conf. Speakers / Attendees (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Conf. Programs Stepping, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Publicity - Stepping (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Womens Subcommittee EOIAA, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Report to the President & the Commission for Women, Final Report (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Coordinating Council on Women (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Proposal: Stepping as AIDS prevention/education (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - SAHC - Mt. Lake Summit, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Kentland Report, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Peacock-Harper Programs (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Mike Two Horses Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Cultural Resource Center (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - South Atlantic Humanities Center (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ferris Visit (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Humanities Misc., 1999 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Humanities Events - Flyers (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Virginia Humanities Conference (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Labyrinth Walk, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Residential Leadership Community (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - VFH Grants - Samples (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Landon, R. Humanities Center, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Virginia Humanities Conf. Proceedings, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - LASC Humanities Consultant Report (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Humanities Review (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - RLC - Leadership (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - RLC History (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Series II: Instruction, Department, and Academic Administrative Materials relating to Virginia Tech
  - HUM 3464 Original Course Proposal (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appalachian Studies Job Description, one-year position, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Appalachian Ministries Educational Resource Center (1st Summer Term), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Appalachian Studies Foundation, Giving Reports (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Appalachian Studies Program, VPI (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Appalachian Research at VT (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Word Weavers at VT (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dorothy F. McCombs Endowed Scholarship (Donors, Applications, Awards, and Programs) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Appalachian Studies at VT (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - VT Appalachian Studies Newsletter (Info, Calls, Distri, content) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Survey of Appalachian Students at VT (ARC), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Appalachian Studies Program Description (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Mudweek Field Trip (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Appalachian Studies Pre-Test (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Appalachian Studies, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Prejudice against Appalachians at Virginia Tech (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Intro to App. Studies, Syllabus, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Student Reflection (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Nellies Cave - Student, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Student Writings (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Student Folklore Papers - Appalachian Studies, Spring, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Faculty Speakers Service (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - American Studies (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Center for Humanities 5 Year Review, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Early Promotional Material, Humanities at VT (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Humanities Faculty Meetings, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Humanities Student Papers, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Margaret P. Hasselman Research, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Humanities Review, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Humanities & Appalachian Studies Histories (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Humanities at VT (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Graduate of Masters of Liberal Arts (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Development of American Indian Studies (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - AIS Teleconference Readings, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - MA of Liberal Studies - Concepts, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Diversity Certificate, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dept. of Interdisciplinary Studies, Dean's Round Table (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Final Report of the Coordinating Council Center of Interdisciplinary Studies, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Native American Studies (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Center for Interdisciplinary Studies, Governance, April 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Case for Interdisciplinary Studies (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series III: Historic Structures at Virginia Tech (mostly Solitude)
  - Solitude Planning (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Solitude Planning - Early (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Solitude Correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Solitude Image Negatives (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Yagow Thesis (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Solitude History with Interviews, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Solitude Advisory Committee, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Solitude Administration (Jean), 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dendrochrology Report, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Solitude Brochure Award, Strathmore Certificate of Silver, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Solitude Funding, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Solitude Fundraising, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Solitude Fundraising, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Outbuilding Construction (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Solitude Historic Structure Report by Gibson Worsham, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Solitude Report (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Historical Landmark Celebration, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Solitude Renovation Space Plans, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Fundraiser, Lee Smith & Barter Theatre, September 30, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Solitude Giving Reports, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Solitude-Historic Structures Report, October 1997 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Solitude Renovation, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Solitude - Spring, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Boyd, Clifton - Outbuilding Reports (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Dedrochronology - Outbuilding Solitude (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Solitude Progress, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Solitude Grants, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Roller-Bottimore Foundation, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Solitude Parking Plans, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Solitude Fundraising - Spring, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Class of 1956 Fund for Solitude (est. 2003) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Parsons Foundation - Solitude, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Solitude, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Solitude Resoration, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Solitude, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Historic Structures, Solitude (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Solitude Museum Proposal (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Solitude, Grand Reopening, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Solitude, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "A Time for Solitude" Publication, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Solitude News Stories (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Solitude in the News (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Solitude Restoration Kick-off, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Solitude Restoration, Recommendations Set, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Restoration of Solitude: Existing Conditions Analysis, Restoration Plan, and Schematic Design (Advanced Programming Package," 2009 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Historic Structures Reports, Solitude (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Solitude - National Register Nomination (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - National Register of Historic Places - Registration Form (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Federal Register Guidelines (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Historic Solitude" by Dr. Fine (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - National Speakers Forum Committee (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - VPI&SU Historic Properties (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - VA Dept. Historic Resources & National Trust for Historic Preservation (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - General Assembly Grant - Solitude (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Foundations for Solitude Programs (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Dave Belcher (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Solitude Articles, "A Time for Solitude" (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Notes on Martha Heiskell & Saunders by Terry Lynn Howerd (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Restoration Code 208 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - C.E. Richardson - Solitude Grant (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Old Photo Solitude (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "Historic Solitude" by Elizabeth Fine, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Solitude Fundraiser, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Architecture Drawing of Solitude (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Images - Outbuilding & Prices For K Project (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Images, Solitude Interior, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Solitude Restoration Newsletter (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Phase I - Restoration, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Solitude Greeting Card, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Solitude Advisory Committee (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Solitude Residents (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Solitude Residents Interview w/ Doris & Jim Bland (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - McBride Woodworks, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Solitude Restoration Newsletter & PR (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Sorenson, Leni - Ideas for Solitude, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Solitude Report - Original (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - DVD Solitude Tour Historical Lecture Series (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Outbuilding - Solitude Structure Reports (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Smithfield Preston Foundation (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Fine, Elizabeth, Tour & General Solitude History (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Portraits of Prestons, Robert & Mary (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Solitude Class Ring 1994 & Preston Portraits, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Dale Bleacher Show (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Mildred Ellmore - Solitude (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Solitude Slave History (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Solitude Slave Cabin in Roanoke Times, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Solitude Historic Structure Bids (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - People in the Story of Solitude (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - List of Potential Donors (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Solitude Slides - Historic from Gibson Worsham (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Solitude Invoices / Estimates (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Richard Sanford - Solitude Letters, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Solitude Committee (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Guest Lists, Solitude (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Outbuilding with Photos and Slides (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Termites - Solitude, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Satterwhite, Emily Student Reflections about Solitude (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - McCormick Farm (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Solitude Restoration Newsletter, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Solitude Graphics (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "Solitude" A Home of the Past & Present - By Bonnie Blankenship (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Palmer Collection (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Solitude Fundraising Letters (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Solitude Donation (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Virginia Tech, Progress Meeting, Advanced Programming for Renovation of Solitude, June 22, 2009 (Folder 1)
  - Feasibility Study for Solitude at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, Prepared by Commonwealth Architects 101 Shockoe Slip, Richmond, Virginia (Draft), 2007 (Folder 1)